Oh
hello thanks for tuning in again so
before I say something and give context
for this video
couple housekeeping things is the
circling Institute my company the
courses that we do and all the
gatherings that we do given the
coronavirus we've taken everything
online so it's an opportunity for those
of you that haven't been able to make it
out to San Francisco to in-person can
now join us and come circling online so
what the the info is below you can look
at our Facebook page or the website the
circling Institute links below if you're
interested in working one-on-one with me
and coaching email me links below
okay so originally Chris and I we're
gonna continue our our platonic dialogue
OHS series where we read we read we go
through and we're just gonna read
through all of the Platonic dialogues
and and talk about it and be in the
process of it well it didn't quite go
that way we ended up actually debriefing
and creating kind of PostScript to the
dialogue oats of the four-way
conversation that I just put out a
couple days ago with John verb a key
Jordan Hall Chris and I and it was
really quite interesting of really
taking we really found that
the fireside the campfire gathering
symbol just kept gathering more and more
and more and more we found ourselves
inside of it
debriefing that last conversation and
then in some sense it's kind of going
beyond it and housing it it was really
generative I think you probably haven't
watched it yet but I would imagine you
kind of feel the energy of kind of the
intelligence of it of it speaking
speaking through us and us realizing it
and having just lots of ideas lots of
coherence and a couple times we're kind
of fell off and got that con but then it
kept weaving it back into the metaphor
of of the fire of the fireside and so we
just you know about an hour after that I
ran at a time and but I wanted to post
this as a postscript to that
conversation so enjoy you know a little
bit further back yes yes because we were
talking about it as something already
already going but really actually the
process is much more like building the
fire yeah and then being witness to it
catching and then redirecting the loving
attention to the place where it catches
yeah and then feeding into that place
right and that's why at the beginning
there's a sort of a beautiful
awkwardness sometimes at the beginning
of those conversations because it's like
trying to lay the kindling to lay the
faggots to lay the wood so that at some
point nobody knows where the spark is
actually gonna come from really but it
will come if the fire is laid
you know lovingly the and it of course
it is and so it catches totally and
there's that sense of so there's that
sense of faith I think yeah we shall oh
yeah what do you think what would have
happened I really like this metaphor
right of the fire it's beautiful well
what what do you think what would have
happened if you just kind of like go
to that whole conversation again just
imagine it and we had that metaphor of
like oh we're we're gathering the wood
right now and this is what it's like to
gather the wood and light it up and like
I wonder what that whole if you just
kind of replayed it of like we had that
frame or that symbol to look through if
that if you did when you imagine it what
do you see when I look through that
symbol of like oh that beginning where
it's like a little bit awkward and like
oh you're like oh it's just coordinated
and if we knew it oh yeah this is the
part this is the part where we're
gathering the wood and we're setting
everything yes yes well I I think that I
think that understanding it with that
metaphoric language actually helps to
foster the faith in the yeah and the
dialogue I mean I'm already too
obviously just supposed to have faith in
the dialogue because if its participants
in because we've done it before
yeah but I think I think in moments if
only in those brief moments where the
faith begins to flag somewhat or stalls
a little bit or falls into lapses into
some form of uncertainty then the actual
the metaphor of the language actually
bares the faith out because you
understand the role of that particular
moment of process in the in the in the
end the masterpiece of the overall
process I know that the what we're doing
now has meaning not for its own sake but
for what it will then lay and avail for
further down this road yeah right so
that you know moments of shifting their
moments of trying to you know the
moments of forced moments of trying to
it's a sort of moments of the shuffling
at the beginning is all in service of
laying the proper five so I think that's
what the metaphor does for me it's it's
you put your finger on it beautifully
it's the fostering of faith yeah it's
the fostering of faith if I if we take
the time carefully to lay the fire to
lay its conditions and this mark will
catch it we see through with faith
so my awkward
right it's like an awkwardness or
admired disheveled this or a wandering
and then we just go this is that part in
which were of course we're awkward and
we're wondering and there were off
balance and this is the part there's
something about that that connects that
it makes it transparent in somehow the
end the end becomes your presence right
yes exactly exactly the fire becomes
present before it ignites the fire
becomes present before it ignites and I
mean if we really if we wanted to strain
the metaphor with a little bit more
specificity we could almost say mmm for
that like each piece of kindling is a
particular proposition if we wanted to
fold it into the typology of knowing
well that might be something actually we
might want to think about doing with
this metaphor is to see how it can
perfuse the typology of knowing because
then each bit of kindling each piece of
wood what not that you lay on the fire
is a proposition that's meant to help to
foster the conditions for the process
that will ultimately Kindle wait a
minute did you just put a piece of
kindling in the fire just now because I
had that feeling if something got lit up
ah ah so perhaps that yes the prop of
that perhaps the claim was also an
enactment of the process that it was
trying to describe I should be so lucky
um yeah yeah there's something this mmm
this is interesting i we didn't talk
about this the other day but there's
something to this
there's something about that moment that
particular moment right where this
realization of like the very thing that
I'm talking about is becomes the thing
that's actually happening or talking yep
did that there's something about die
dialo ghosts that I think is where topic
person talking right become the same
thing yep but there's also this element
of where it's the dialogue oh so you
find yourself of it in it yes yes create
it Jesus you fall into stride with it
yeah you start to properly trace its
motions your emotions become its motions
because you've fallen into it almost
into its gravitation yes your motion
it's like that it's like the origin of
motion converts the motion is not of you
like right you're it's not of your own
motility as it were if I can use that
metaphor
it's that yourt enacted from your
enacted by a motion that you've now's
trained you have now stepped into yes
see this is so your motion and its
motion become identical because they
share all of a sudden they share the
same nature and that's that that's that
the affinity of antiquity right that's
what I think that the neoplatonist are
trying to talk about right this for the
motion of the spheres being in train
with the motion of the spheres as it
were yeah it's also I don't not exactly
sure what is fits but I'm just I'm and I
think I'm I mean II I've been trying to
integrate this this Aristotle reading I
did about at least from this author
there's a Haida Gary is somebody who's
like a looking reading Aristotle through
Heidegger right basically and mmm author
really he highlighted how you know I'm
probably gonna do a whole lot of damage
there so let this thing just burn in the
fire but like my understanding is a lot
of what moved Aristotle to write was
this tension that was left open between
I think with perimeters between up until
amenities yeah yeah is that which
doesn't change and non-being is that
which chain
or moves and an Aristotle saying like no
there's got there's a tension there that
there's no not being if it moves or
changes when there's no being that which
endures are skates the same and where he
went at it from is he had to show how
movement wasn't just antic but it was
ontological mmm movement was a part of
osya right this kind of pushing up is
not okay not a thing that moves but a
feature of the feature of being itself
right and I'm just kind of getting the
sense of like being well when you're
talking about moving right like I'm
moving and that which moves is moving me
I recognize we're both being moved by
what was right right but that sense of
potentials like that yeah
movement and change is being right the
way the being it's got its good and some
level and if I remember right in this in
the for Aristotle it was like well how
does how do you get at how do you show
that that that movement is an
ontological structure hmm that fits no
that seems to fit because then I think
pal but yeah you're right
because I think I think for Aristotle
the movement the movement is always a
movement to the T loss of the nature
intrinsic to a particular thing right or
to the category of a particular thing
everything moves in the direction of its
simplicity Eicher almost an again almost
in a gravitational way right things that
fall to earth fall to earth because they
are other as they belong on earth as it
were and so then the movement of all
things is a movement in a it's Tillich
movement yes which
which which which explains how the
movement is of being ultimately and not
even picking up is fair to say that even
picking up the wood or the the
propositions to make the fire is already
being given by the Talos which isn't
here that when we light the fire we find
ourselves I'm just kind of getting this
sense of I really like this what you
said about like the fire of dialog oh
s--- there's the setting up the fire
there's printing the rocks around
there's gathering the wood and then
there's pudding oh yeah being the
propositions upon which we yeah we set
into this newt we enact into into
different levels of no way yes yes and
the idea that the put that the
propositional situating of the deal
logos by the laying of the wood as the
kindling is connected ultimately to the
participatory enactment of its embers of
its actual sparking and that the thing
that connects the laying of the
propositions the building of the fire to
the ultimate enactment of its flame is
faith that's like you pinning that on
that particular term is perfect right
because that cotton what that means in a
way is that there's actually kind of an
it well and I'm not not new in that it's
perhaps it was an implicit before but
new in the sense I think that you've
made it explicit guy but perhaps what is
actually what is actually the thing the
very the disposition of engagement the
interesa that opens continuity between
the ways of knowing is in fact faith
yeah
okay so there again so like the
disposition of interesa right the being
involved in the immersion into right
that opens continuity and the cascading
transmutation of one
way of knowing down into the other right
so to go from propositional knowing into
the grounding propositional knowing down
back into participatory knowing that the
grounding of one way of knowing and it's
more primordial and decedent way of
knowing that the disposition that
actually enables and fosters the
orientation from the first to the fourth
way of knowing is actually the
disposition of faith yeah and I never
thought of faith in those terms before
that the faith that that the reason that
you build the fire is because you have
faith in the building of the fire yeah
that the building of the fire will
culminate in the kindling of the flame
and and that's a beautiful way of
thinking about the process because we
kept talking the other day about you
know how beautiful the flame is when
it's cultivated how it changes our
relationship to the phenomenology and
the ontology of the world right what it
does to our relationship with being once
ignited but we actually didn't talk
about although perhaps performed the
process of actually building it from the
ground up yes yes and that deserves just
as much if not more attention because I
mean we can all appreciate we are all
galvanized by a beautiful fire right
we're a good fire is appreciable to
almost universally appreciable right we
have no problem appreciating the beauty
of a good fire but we do have difficulty
with actually producing it or
participating in its production and
that's where the faith comes in right
and the form of fire so one of the
things that so that's sort of
interesting and then the whole metaphor
uh metaphors about the divine spark the
pneuma and the conscience and like
of those and then all of those abundant
theological metaphors and philosophic
metaphors of antiquity involving flame
involving the relationships between
flame and spiritus and faith I'll start
to pour into this campfire now because
now it's host to a world of spiritual
analogies write it in some way that
flame as it burns and you know this if
you've made campfires right especially
if you had to work for it like if you
had to chop yeah right and you light it
in it there is this interesting quality
where it's really clear cuz if you've
ever tried to light a fire when it's
been windy or something right like or
it's brutal sure so it's you really
clear that there's it takes it takes at
least divine divinities to work with you
you can't make it lit yeah the quality
of like grace like ah yes um harnessing
of the elements like the surfing
metaphor yeah but part of what clothes
cuz the fire that yeah the fire that you
chopped the wood for right versus the
fire that just I don't know you bought
you bought the lumber at Kmart or
something right like and he put gas on
it right versus he chopped the wood and
he did all the work and like you and you
brought it up he brought it up there and
that it lights up part of the beauty
that shines through is the whole thing
as grace including your labor including
your sacrifices including the death of
your most prized propositions as they
burn up in flame and then and then
here's what I also love you said
something you said something just
earlier about the fact that you know if
the proposition maybe if the proposition
turns out to be defunct or the
proposition turns out to be turns out
not to be as operable
you know you'll throw it into the fire
and it'll just burn there and what's
interesting is that what's interesting
about the metaphor but the metaphor can
actually devour that situation as well
in both literally and figuratively
because what happens is let's say you
know a proposition the relief of a
proposition will often only be distinct
and discernible after the fact of its
use so if you throw a proposition into
the fire and that proposition actually
doesn't catch or ignite at the moment of
its offering what is likely to happen is
that when the fire does catch when the
dialogic process truly Kindles and takes
over and takes on the life of its own it
will retro actively Illume all of those
propositions that came before it
that could not manage to ignite it at
the time of their offering so in other
words the bit of kindling that you threw
into the fire that didn't catch before
once other pieces have caught it too
inevitably will also be engulfed by them
interesting wow this is really like I
mean everybody's getting the sense of
this fire as a symbol it's really
gathering everything when you say my god
like even like our symbol even host:this
it even includes the lack of this or
that yeah I'm feeling I can feel a
gathering in and if something is about
like a fire that's like especially one
that's slamming hot you can feel it's
sucking things in and then combusting it
right that that whole thing yes yes
exactly and the other thing that's also
kind of beautiful about it is that I'm
thinking of that equidistance we were
talking about our four-way conversation
we're talking about the sort of the
importance of the equidistance of the
individuals to and from the fire and I
mean what happens when someone gets too
close to it as well right I mean that's
almost a reflection that deters there's
something about the dynamic of the
process that actually deters the nurses
impulse because if you get too close to
the fire right John was bringing up
those examples or I can't remember if it
was that and that or another
conversation recently was bringing up
those examples those mythic exam right
the Icarus examples of those who get too
closer to the sort who'd get too close
to the source of their of their vitality
and if someone gets too close to the
fire obviously you know they that's
damaging it's damaging potentially to
the fire it's damaging also to the
individual and it's damaging to the
overall dynamic of the communal that's
gathered around it so that also feeds
into the aptness of that metaphor
because the equidistance is not an
incidental feature of the process it is
a necessary feature of the process you
cannot be too far away from the fire or
too close to the fire its figuration
actually prescribes the orientation and
configuration around it the figuration
of the fire prescribes its configuration
right you everyone has to be situated in
such a way as to optimize it
yeah and optimize its effect on them and
their relationship to and through it
with and to one another boy this some
may be it should have been obvious
because of its its its its its perennial
use in our mythos but this symbol is
remarkably remarkably exemplary of of
day logos in ways that in ways that we
have even yet to discover I think or
qualify based on what and to what degree
its burned and just everything that has
gathered just now and just talking about
it yeah it's like we haven't even
touched the Sun someone who's got that
kind of quality to it yeah well then
that's the I mean that's even then there
is the property of an exhaust ability
yeah right right we haven't even gotten
to it yet right yeah there's a there's
this beautiful night the inexhaustible
eternality of it I that that that that
even when we think we have exhausted
it's eternity has yet to begin yes right
which is a great way of thinking about
it's an accessibility at the invest and
once it
yes realizing it's an exhaust ability I
am anything but exhausted right right
like it's inexhaustibility but it's it's
this quality of like that's something
about it where I think I'm wondering if
this is what John was highlighting or
shining about you know because one of
the things in that conversation he was
like well okay well what is it that if
dialogue OSes could be a way of being in
length great this kind of Socratic faith
what is it that how can we exemplify it
in a way that actually has it be
something that people will just find
themselves doing because by virtue of
being drawn towards it and and my
recollection is what that's when the
inquiry about beauty straightest right
yes that's right there's beauty like so
so my experience of just kind of coming
to this is it's beautiful yes really and
that the beauty and the functionality
are actually inseparable
because a beautiful fire is also a
working fire and a working fire is also
a beautiful fire in functionality and
beauty can become symbiotic like mmm
mutually disclose and enhance and
participate with one another that's like
the opposite of those business meetings
we were talking about oh yeah
it's precisely the inverse of those
business we were talking about those
business meetings that endeavor to
colleague and endeavor like like like
the like the narcissistic impulse that
endeavor to come to a point right the
ideal it's arson the idolatrous impulse
that endeavors to come to a point to
achieve its closure to a point and there
is a place for that of course there is
some ways in which some situations in
which we do need
that functionally but it's it did this
is exactly the opposite this opens out
it opens out and there's in in terms of
the functionality right so basically
well what what what has is bothered
chopping wood right and setting up the
stones and finding the right place which
is also really finding the right place
yeah yeah say more about that well
what's interesting is there's got to be
in a clearing uh-huh you can't like make
your fire in the dense jungle like
surrounded by a bunch of things that you
can't see it's actually in the clearing
that the fire uh-huh right cuz huh got
it the sparks go up and you oh yeah yeah
yeah and I'm just of course you can kind
of hear this turn a phrase around it
which is like heidegger's notion of you
know the way that he talks about
thinking as you know he doesn't really
have he doesn't have views like he just
got he's gone on like trails in the
forest and the and rings of thought and
thought you know following it not
knowing where it's going and then
there's these moments that are almost
like by grace where the the thickness of
the the forests all this and opens up
into the clearing right yes yes what's
interesting about like the shaman who
works his way through the narrow tunnel
only to open back out into the sunlight
and has that gestalt shift in
perspective that reopens the world right
that the enclosure and its opening right
which is such a primordial motif for
mimesis
and it's like the sex I know in
Heidegger speak in it in a sense sign
being there is is precisely we are a
thrown openness clearing right the
gathers like you could say that like I
get this sense I'm just like with the
sunset right right the the sunset it
requires my constraints my limit D
actually finitude yes yes in that
since it becomes a clearing of the of
the what would otherwise be a a a self
transparent or self opaque either way
dominance of itself totally opaque but
then there's we're born and a little
perspective and then the whole every all
that shows up is cosmos yeah right and
there's that there's something done
gather devices are death right yes yes
oh that's good and so then that feeds
again back into and through the opening
of the metaphor because part of the
building of the building of the fire the
cultivation of the fire of the campfire
is constrained by the givenness of the
environment right you you you can choose
your place within but but still within
certain constraints right you cannot
decide to go and build a fire anywhere
in the world as it were you have to
build right the fire is still located
within the given nests of the
constraints that your actuality has
provided yeah and and so there the
cultivation of the fire has to take
place and be drawn from the wellspring
that is available to you by your throne
nests as it were yeah
now so can we think about this so
there's that there's that you know and
being in time where it talks about the
you know that if the two modes of being
there or human being right if authentic
and authentic and I think it's something
like this is very difficult I keep
thinking I understand this and then it
slips away so it's one of those things
that seem to be was infinite horizons of
continually realizing that it's
inexhaustible but but this sense of like
wool okay the inauthentic mode of the
clearing is when the clearing does not
take itself as a clearing or an openness
for the world
old to occur right or show or shine
forth as phenomena but instead it's the
perpetuation of idle talk and
inauthenticity which is to see myself as
one of one of the things amongst other
things in the world that then acts and
sexuality not realizing that like even
even its inauthenticity is given by this
primordial sense of our finitude that we
bring or the clearing that we bring we
cover it over by not seeing it but but
demonstrating it being the clearing that
demonstrates me being you know like the
person trying to prove himself and gasa
yes yes being the ball rolling so
there's it so there's it's interesting
if we say that like okay it I mean one
way that we can we can look at this as
we look at Dyea logos is it's almost
like the it's a I don't even know if its
opposite but it's totally other than
idle talk
yes it's like what is the difference
between yeah like the fire and building
it and the dialogue oh s--- right and
then what would be like what like what
is idle talk
what is the chitchat what is even like
that that sense of just keeping things
going yes like I'm wondering about I'm
wondering about like if we look at if
that's a if that's useful or hmm or
fruitful is it different would that you
burn is it hmm right
is it the smoke is it yes
so perhaps hmm I love just throwing
something over there and then just
seeing what happens yes through that log
in the fire yes yes yes yes well that's
the thing where I wait we argue er
gathering ourselves to it even as we're
trying to describe what it is that we're
gathering
ooh and so if I yeah so okay let's try
and then really really really dig
ourselves then into the body of the
metaphor so I mean in some sense any
perhaps any stick of wood could
potentially serve as kindling for a
dialogic process even it begun idly cuz
sometimes if you think about it
sometimes so-called idle chatter does in
fact transmute itself into diello goes
right conversations that seem banal at
their outset can at times
suddenly Kindle it does happen to the
great surprise of their participants
sometimes idle conversations can
suddenly reveal a dialogic spirit and be
possessed by that dialogic spirit
unbeknownst to and unwitting to the
people who have have have have have sort
of laid the conditions for it yes but
there is I think a dichotomy to be drawn
perhaps between the willfully cultivate
the Dora will willfully let's leave will
out of it for second knowingly
cultivated diya logos and the
unknowingly cultivated diya logos and
that could be something like this is a
bit crude yeah crude in the sense of
it's supposed to a blunt way to treat
the metaphor but it could be the just
difference between a well-chosen stick
of wood and an in attentively chosen
stick of wood right people who know how
to build fires know what kinds of wood
to use and the uninitiated tend to just
pick any stick up off the ground and
think that it's going to catch right but
of course people who are practiced that
building a fire know that you you need a
certain kind of wood needs to be dry you
know certain sizes are good you need to
layer it in certain ways so that there's
an accidental or unlooked to potential
implicit in dialog that it can erupt
unexpectedly even from sticks of wood
that aren't well suited to it yeah
accidental successes are very
motivational
because accidental successes actually
encourage people who have produced
something by accident to seek out the
thing that they produced by accident but
to seek it out more knowingly dialog us
is perfect fits into that metaphor right
if you think about it because I mean I
think in a very first conversation we
were talking about this that
conversations like are big going you
know back some months of rhetorics
conversation some conversations have
marked meaningfulness in life in a way
that few other things can or do and in
many cases I know for me those
conversations that have ended up
erupting into dialogic flame have not a
erupted into dialogic flame because we
were building a dialogic fire they just
happened because we were throwing sticks
of wood
on into a pit and at some point it
caught but the fact that it caught the
fact that it caught was was the
beginning of the revelation of dialo
goes and what dialogue goes can be and
do and so then we return to it more and
more purposefully thereafter knowing how
transformational it can become and so I
guess getting back to your question
about you know sort of the difference
between the idle the idle the idle
chatter and the the purposefully
dialogic chatter maybe it's simply a you
know a matter of a matter of be a haven
idle in no I idle chatter Dyke I think I
don't think idle chatter is as I am I
don't feel as unkind toward idle chatter
as I know some people do because I think
even idle chatter can accidentally
foster the conditions of intimate
relating yes
even when we're not conscious of the
intent to do so totally it's almost a
matter a difference of it's a difference
of kind in in the purposefulness but
it's a difference of degree in its
potential to offer the kindling right if
that makes any sense I'm not even yeah
yes well it's it's interesting I mean
this is this is the tricky part
right and this is kind of hot this is
hard to grasp but you have to kind of
think ontologically about this but it's
not like authenticity good you know
that's bad no it's like right it wasn't
for idle talk and in authenticity take
out the value judgment on that
authenticity is like well it's going on
in your head if you sit down and try to
quiet your mind all the thoughts that
you don't notice that you're having that
when you notice you let them go what is
that on some level like one way of
thinking about that well that's the
culture in the cultural practices
keeping themselves going right right if
there wasn't gossip and all these kind
of things built in that it in there is
that sense of like there's something
actually quite exquisite and kind deep
about like hello how you doing I'm doing
fine yeah yeah yeah in other words the
automaticity of it is also a propulsion
of it right yes yes but at some point
that which is automatic now that one
point was probably a fire a long time
ago like was a spark the then right but
then okay cuz just look at that so it's
like let's look at that so it's like
that's the spark that then became an
idea an insight that went into action
that then created norms around it and
then structures and built in and then
the very spark and the norm became in
they no longer you can no longer feel
the flame but they're like what we sit
on top of to put fire in the way right
yeah yeah yeah that's right that's right
so what I think what probably is
something like that I'm wondering this
is if this is like
working within what we're talking about
that okay so that's like the basic
cultural affordance yeah for dialogue
all of that machinery unthinking
machineries the basic cultural apparatus
that allows us to even contemplate the
possibility of such a thing
exactly I think about it like I think
about it it's like the it's like the
vine or the foliage that kind of comes
and weaves itself together but knowing
link to itself really it's kind of
automatic but deeply intelligent and
then authenticity something like the
sprout something yes the flowering and
it blossoms the effleurage then it comes
back down and disrupts this yeah grates
it and then that thing down here becomes
part of the right that's why it's
difficult to say like yeah okay that's -
okay this is cool so then then the
authentic cultivation in some sense
rests upon it rests upon sort of a
primordial sort of an inauthentic or an
unconscious primordial affordance in the
form of the cultural systems that we
have functioning as our givenness and
some in some something like that yes
and I'm wondering about like I think
part of the thing of what kind of
authentic is this paradox of the flame
right like I think on some level there's
always this experience when the flame
lights there is this experience of like
it was already there that part of its
profundity is it it is it's is the light
by which I just saw was the light that
lit yes right and it disclosed it so so
inauthentic see is the disclosure of the
withdrawal of the fire so on some level
it's like you and I are talking and
we're lit by the fire and we're
completely of everything that we see but
there is no sense of the realization
that it's the fire
that's lighting us is by means of the
logos that any of this is at all and I
uh I don't I just I use the lights I eat
with the lights I see with the light we
speak with the light but I think it's
it's it's on some level that it the
light discloses as it reveals so
something like where it erupts would be
something like we're at some point
somebody goes wait a minute okay how the
hell did we and what is it that's
lighting all of this right
and there's the it's because I think
that there's that quality of
inauthenticity has to do with the
forgetfulness or the COS right right and
so the remembrance and revelation of the
of the of the sort of the fluorescence
cast by the light it is something yeah
where's Plato talks about like all
knowledge is remembering like yeah like
that quality of like that we don't have
knew like that sense of like we don't
have new ideas in it really
experientially makes sense when there's
an insight it doesn't feel like I
discovered something new it's actually
that just sense of like oh yeah yeah
it's like oh damn concealment yeah that
thing that like the you're backing into
I can think of what Socrates is all you
know about backing into right right
right see right yes and so it's the
realization of remembrance that also
entails the realization of your your
your prior forgetfulness in the light of
that emerging logos totally that
constitutes the the countenance of
authenticity yes where you can see that
the lineaments of the world as they
present to you are owed to are owed to
sort of the burgeoning luminosity i'll
which do which is not which is not which
is not sudden in its nature but sudden
in your remembrance is that
Clee yes exactly in fact in your
remembrance you realize like oh it's
been working the whole time in fact it
like it do with this was coming and and
you have this gratitude for a process
that's been unfolding that didn't need
your recognition okay clearly had an
intelligibility on its own and that's
that experience of trust and faith that
opens up in those moments of insight
right and so so here's the thing I'm
wondering about and it seems like this
this kind of kind of weaves this in here
like so this thing about like this
difference between I really appreciate
what you're saying is yeah like let's
not discredit idle talk and chitchat and
social norms and like there's something
really deep there because some of the
best deal logo system than the ones that
have just erupted within that right
totally
and so if we look at if we look at the
ones that we actually build the fire for
and we construct and we we consciously
bring in the wood and we go through the
awkwardness and the difficulty and then
we and we do that right so the
difference between the two and but also
the connection between the two so this
is an experience I was reminded of
working with with clients and I've I
think I've come to some recent
experiences with some clients that have
been really really particularly profound
they're just reminded me of this right I
think it's remind me of this is I have
to say the craziest thing right for I
think for people the most amount of
suffering is is if you're saying deeply
saying right and your parents are crazy
and then everyone else around you is
crazy right but you're the same one but
then because you're around everybody
that's crazy your sanity actually is a
self evident sense of like this is like
valid intelligent
and everyone around all they can do is
mirror back like that's wrong and
there's this whole experience of like
having to go completely against this
innate intelligibility there's so many
double binds and acrobats and and for
whatever reason I've just I've noticed
that a lot that the people who have had
the most weirdest double buying
sufferings and contortions in their
lifes and struggles actually what when
we start to uncover everything they
realize like oh my God my mom was like a
schizophrenic and my dad was like a
narcissist and they used to torture me
and I I just got used to that and and
hmm and I could see the like I could
actually I had a a sane response but I
had no agreement my life did not reflect
my sanity my sanity got a reflection of
that I'm insane and that really
intelligent people kind of going through
that beautiful people but then to watch
them so in particular like so we'll I'll
be working with them and then they'll
have this experience where I'll be just
like they'll have this experience of
being seen the first time myself or
something yeah totally
like actually remember one time this guy
had a crazy mother but most of the time
are like a parenting usually happens but
in within the household so no one really
sees it hmm it was obvious that his mom
was crazy right like you said that all
this kind of stuff and then we had her
in for a session and she did she was
predictably crazy and we're walking
we're walking away and she went home and
I was walking him back to his car and
he's like he was like that was crazy
right and I'm like kind of goes without
saying it's like yeah that was really
intense that I just imagine what it must
have been like to grow up in that he's
like what wait it no you saw that that
thing that she did when she like spun
her head around three times and it was
real right yeah I'm like
for my for my life was was pretty crazy
yeah and there's this experience of you
know right what because that very
experience of her used to get him more
and more in trouble right and in that
moment their shared reality about like
now that's really true yeah and when and
then me and then from that point on he
started to be he started to have noticed
more moments in his life that glowed
reality right and so like this
experience of being seen deeply seen on
one level usually there's this confusion
because it's tied up with like guys
really really great or their therapist
really great or the counselors really
great right and they may be but it's
like it's it's not they don't they don't
recognize like actually this this is
just simply the experience of them being
seen in it in the light that's actually
reflected he's actually shown back as it
is on some level right and then they
have that experience and I've watched
this over and over again where they have
this experience and then they start
their let to all the places that light
up like that they can start to see it
and then they start to gravitate towards
that and they start to have friends that
then see and they start to restore what
has always been saying but unrequited
right and I'm wondering about like that
sense of but until that connections made
of like where that guy was like that was
crazy right look yes yeah whoa like it's
yeah cuz then cuz then all of a sudden
through you he was able to encircle
himself into a perspective yeah exactly
exactly and then he was able to encircle
himself and his family together into a
perspective because he had you be
holding it right and and it could could
proximate himself in in the carriage of
your understanding and that's not
something obviously they had as disposal
before yes exactly right oh my god what
a profound experience that must have
been
for him and I'm wondering about like
this okay there is these fires back to
the fire right there's the carefully lit
ones we come together we take our
property and we it it's a ritualistic
sense of it where this is it's like what
calls us forward is the fuck is the
future or the tailless of the fire
itself and and then there's the erupting
sea I'm wondering about if something
like those intentional fires are
something like the experience of that
was crazy right yes that was right this
experience of where we we we gather that
intensely we experience it on purpose
that there's something about having that
experience that makes us be able to like
see recognize the source of that which
is lighting the intelligibility which
lights everything in these moments and
we become more apt to be prone for write
visits from Socrates will say right
right right that's right that's right
and so when someone comes along like you
did in this situation and shows and it
might take only a couple of strokes to
rearrange that to rearrange that fire in
a way that it might be yeah in a way
that it might be better ignited or more
reliably ignited but all it does is it
takes someone to come in and to adjust
the craft for you or to show you the
craft in such a way that then then
you're able to actually reproduce
something that only erupts spontaneously
when when it lacks the training when it
lacks the attention yes yes here's that
part of the firework I have to go pee
that's an important part of every fire
you always have to stray away from it
into the darkness and become the fur
thank you for lighting the door
this in such a way that it becomes I'll
be thank you thank you in one second
this this campfire metaphor is really
becoming enough so that so much so that
I think it's I don't know I think you
and II will need to dwell need to take
it with us and we'll need to think about
how the metaphor itself can be used to
beautify the process that we're
partaking us yeah you know that like I
love I mean I love the fact that you
used it as the the thumbnail for the
conversation the other day I almost
think that it like I don't know I I
almost think that it it's something that
can come to represent these projects
that were undertaking almost in a more
formal way yeah yeah and I know I mean I
guess I guess Jordan was saying for some
in some cases that already has come to
represent that for some people and
that's good that's good but IIIi think
that we I think I think that we need to
keep keep this in hand will then emerge
and even even just that that it's
already come to represent this and yeah
we're consciously articulating what's
already here is exemplifies the very
thing we're talking about right right
and so to I guess to use your sort of
high daguerreian way of thinking about
it where that in coming to becoming more
conscious of it sadness is a kind of
high daguerreian authentication of its
emergence right
right to come on we're level of its
light by which we are knowing this
process yes yes we're hearing seeing the
light that's already lit and then right
bringing into language and responding
and articulating what we're hearing
right cuz I think that there is that
sense of which was it Sean Kelly who
wrote a book with Dreyfuss called all
like I've read it I'll think shining
yeah yeah keep that he's got like a 20
hour recording of his of his class on
late Heidegger it's really good I really
went along
okay actually there's similarities
between the two of you I'd be
interesting to for you to hear this but
he you know it's basically in in the
Dreyfuss way of teaching which which is
basically Dreyfuss isn't trying to teach
you anything he's up there and he's just
gets he gets up learning reads and he
gets stumped and he's like all right
what the hell is he talking about great
city just let's learn ray goes up there
and he learns in front of everybody and
it just draws and gathers this is like
really messy but but exciting deeply
impactful way of teaching right here
houses the humility yeah and he's super
clumsy and like geeky and just awkward
and and unconscious of it in a very kind
of classic professorial kind of way it
jobs a lot more inherently
composed and gathered and articulate and
poetic and but he really kind of does
the same thing he gets up there and he
reads it and he's okay and you can use
you can literally see him start the cup
and what I like about it is is actually
what I what what I think Kelly was
excavating out of later Heidegger where
is like okay how do we respond to to the
event right what is what's the German
word for that Nauticus tell that's the
opposite of it but whatever that word is
that means that the event of unconcealed
meant right Alethea it's it it's its
Heidegger's way of speaking non Anto on
to--they alle theologically right like
speaking being but not through a
metaphysics of some kind right whatever
that is
yeah and what he said is like well well
how do you how do you cultivate like how
do you prepare for the coming of the
event right let's say great well we say
get down to it
like well you make yourself you make
yourself in a sense transparent or open
to the ability to be open to to be
struck by that which is whispering that
couldn't you couldn't hear unless you
were open to be struck by in such a way
that the hearing of which that calls you
forth to speak and in that sense of that
sense of the order between like it
matters I think between like there's a
listening that you're hearing it so
deeply that like that you hear it and
then you articulate it but then there's
the hearing it speaking it hearing
expedia to where they're like the same
thing mmm we're listening and hearing or
harkening is still prior right mm-hmm
like you're so open to it you're so of
it you're so clearly listening into it
that the the harkening of it is that
which gives testimony to having heard it
right yes yes that's the way that
everything's gonna change
right right right
well that oh that's really good
hmm i okay I'm just letting that sink
I'm letting that sink
beautifully put guy you know I probably
need to need to actually close this I
mean we can get together tomorrow or
Monday or something like that and go I
mean it's not okay it's so good no this
is a great like group we couldn't we
clearly we clearly felt the need to yeah
this is clearly the path that we really
wanted to go down so I'm glad we did
that
I'm glad we gave gave in to our we gave
in to the impulse of it
thank you Socrates thank you yeah yeah
yeah good stuff yeah we can pick this up
at any point we could do it tomorrow we
could do the next day either or no
problem great doing this with you this
is so wrong
this was so fun yeah it was so you and I
like having you someone close to me in
my life and I I'm I'm really grateful
for that too I was just thinking about
this the other day actually guy that
like it's only been like a fetter no I
don't know how long it's been it really
hasn't been that long at all that we've
been sitting and having these
discussions and yet I feel it like I
feel like I know you very well even
though the time has been so brief it's
been so abundant yeah that it's it's the
time is really not an accurate way of
measuring how it how it feels at all and
and and also I'm still like some novelty
of the fact that like like we're at such
a distance but we're still able to do
this in the way that we are and it feel
yeah anyway I it's so it's just so cool
and I'm so grateful for it and yeah I'm
grateful to have you like constantly
around to talk to
both when I when we're actually talking
and even when we're not talking to you
yeah that said I'm really good you know
I'm grateful I'm grateful for your
friendship and and and just grateful for
how rich it's become in such a short
period of time yeah in even that sense
of just like my nervous system it's not
even it's like
it's like even my nervous system was
like right actors he's a lifer or it's
like as if I've known you you know
there's people that there's not there's
not a whole lot of formality that comes
up there's forming spontaneously but not
but not not the sense of I'm getting to
know you and I'm orienting it's like I
haven't really experienced much of that
with you and it's did you seem to feel
my nervous system just reached pre
reflectively respond to you that way in
just the way that you were talking about
yeah yeah I have that exact same
experience it's a gift a gift I will
readily accept right on I'm impressed
getting especially given this
traumatized oh my god you you you vocal
I mean you must you must know that
you're - you're too humble to say so but
like you must know this about yourself
that you inspire you inspire a
confidence and a and a level of sort of
intimate disclosure and people that is
so room I mean it's that's I mean you're
you're I mean obviously right that's
you're so much of what you do is based
on that gift of yours which obviously I
know it's cause it's a cultivated gift
in addition to just being an innate one
but like dude if you do it you like it's
from Marcus II I'm struggling even to
find words for it it's remarkable it's
just remarkable and it's inspiring and
and and that's what's made it so easy
yeah
how about feeling this is at the center
I think this is in any we haven't gotten
to this part with with Plato but like to
have a feeling when he spoke in our last
in or less when we when he referred to
friendship as a God I feel on some level
there's there's some feeling I have that
like a lot of these these digital
campfires right these dialog osis that
are enacting that on some level I feel
in some very profound but like super
simple way has something to do with a
very deep notion
friendship yes yeah yes yes but not like
it's funny it's like not like friendship
that is the result of some some process
but more like some friendship or way of
being or comporting that friendship is
just present that's what I think I meant
by like the sense of intimacy with you
is as if I've known you for a long time
right it's not it's like what would
normally take going through a process
with somebody right getting you know
that there's it I think it's weak on
some level I would imagine because on
some level as was John really pointed
out one point like one of the things he
says like it's nice having peers yeah in
the literal sense of the word right like
that work he really on some level we're
peering at the same madness yeah like we
who aspire as he presently loves that
gets invoked in the affinity to share
that that is just unbelievable totally
totally and no amount of time is
sufficient to foster that if the if the
intrinsic natures of those people that
just need the spontaneous chemistry that
you cannot calculate or premeditate it
if that's not there no amount of time
can create that I was just as you were
saying us I was thinking like I mean I
feel I know you and am more known by you
now after such a short period of time
then I feel about people who I've known
for years and years and years and and
people who I do care about and I value
and are important to me but but that
there's not that's we're not looking at
the same things and we're not looking in
the same direction yeah and the way that
we are you and I are and you know we are
with John so on and and you can't
that's not reducible to any amount of
time it's not reducible to anything
concrete
it just emerges or it doesn't and that's
what I mean by saying it's a gift it's
like it's a it's and and the god of
friendship you're right thinking about
it as like a spirit
a good way of thinking about for that
reason yeah spirit descends on the
relationship or a doesn't you know and I
guess because of what were peering at
ultimately are is timeless yes we're
oriented towards timeless
I guess that quickens things it sure
does
right it sure does yeah cuz it lifts you
out of the bat like it lifts us out of
time all together and so the passage of
time becomes like you're relevant
interesting it just oh it's the vertical
against the opens up to the vertical
right yeah yeah and and that I mean
that's happened from the very beginning
here which I'm so I'm so so grateful for
yeah
great being infinite with you likewise
my friend also loved my friend so much
so much so we'll get I'll text you and
we'll schedule it that's what the Plato
again sounds great
okay see you soon